<Document>
# Botany

Botany in Nuclear 14 is about growing food, medicinal plants, and useful extracts for your settlement. Plant products can be eaten raw, cooked, ground into extracts, or turned into ingredients for medicine and other crafting recipes.

## Growing Basics

Most growers use either simple soil beds or proper hydroponic planters. Soil is cheap and reliable, while hydroponics gives clearer visual feedback about plant health.

## Soil Beds
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14Soil"/>
</Box>
Soil can be made in the crafting menu from compost. It is the simplest way to farm, but it does not provide the flag indicators that hydroponic trays do, so you need to inspect plants directly to judge their condition.

The plant life cycle is as follows:
- [color=lightgreen]Empty[/color]: no water, seeds, or nutrients
- [color=lightgreen]Moist[/color]: you've added water to it (e.g., from a bottle or bucket).
- [color=lightgreen]Ready to Plant[/color]: you've added water and nutrients (i.e., fertilizer).
- [color=lightgreen]Planted[/color]: you've added a seed or cutting to it.
- [color=lightgreen]Ready to Harvest[/color]: you've waited for the plant to grow.
- [color=lightgreen]Sample Taken[/color]: you've taken a sample (seed/cutting)
- [color=lightgreen]Harvested[/color]: you've collected the ripe plants. Some plants will grow again after this. Others will die and need replanting.
- [color=lightgreen]Unhealthy[/color]: You've taken too many samples or sprayed it with deadly chemicals. The plant is not doing well. It will continue to grow. Health can be restored with fertilizer, or you can cut your losses, extract the seed (with pruners) and replant it.
- [color=lightgreen]Old / Withered[/color]: the plant has matured and will soon die. It will still be harvestable, and you can extract seeds, but only for a short period of time. Extract the seed, then pull it up / chop it down.
- [color=lightgreen]Dead[/color]: the plant has been harvested and has stopped growing. It should be pulled up / chopped down. Seeds cannot be extracted.

## Hydroponic Planters
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14HydroponicsPlanter"/>
</Box>
Hydroponic setups are a more advanced way of farming because they add visual flags that indicate plant status at a glance. The underlying growth process is the same as soil, but maintenance is easier because warning signs are visible on the tray.

Hydroponic flag indicators:
- [color=red]Red flag, bottom right[/color]: Dead plant that needs replanting. Use a shovel to remove the plant.
- [color=orange]Weeds[/color]: The environment is suboptimal. Check what's affecting the plant by clicking it with Shift held. It's likely weeds, but it could be unwanted pressure or lack of oxygen. If it's weeds, use a mini-hoe or spray once with herbicide. However, be aware that overuse of herbicides can result in unhealthy plants, possibly even death.
- [color=#0336ff]Blue flag, bottom left[/color]: Water needed. Use a bucket on the water reservoir and fill the tray.
- [color=green]Green flag, top left[/color]: Ready to harvest. Left-click to harvest.
- [color=yellow]Yellow flag, top right[/color]: Nutrients needed. Use any fruit and place it in the soil or get fertilizer from animal manure or by mining.

## Plant Genetics
Plants pass traits to their offspring through seeds and cuttings. By observing good strains, preserving seed stock, and occasionally mutating crops, you can produce hardier and more productive harvests.

## Traits
The phenotype, or visible set of traits a plant expresses, can be identified by growing it and paying attention to how it behaves.

- [color=lightgreen]Bioluminescence[/color]: plants with this trait glow in the dark
- [color=lightgreen]High Yield[/color]: plants with this trait produce more fruit per harvest
- [color=lightgreen]Less Water[/color]: plants with this trait require less water than usual to grow
- [color=lightgreen]Woody[/color]: plants with this trait require sharp tools to harvest
- [color=lightgreen]Long-lived[/color]: plants with this trait live through more harvest cycles before dying
- [color=lightgreen]Low Light[/color]: plants with this trait require less light than usual to grow
- [color=lightgreen]Pest Resistant[/color]: plants with this trait are more resistant to pests
- [color=lightgreen]Seedless[/color]: plants with this trait do not produce viable seeds
- [color=lightgreen]Weed Resistant[/color]: plants with this trait suppress weed growth

You can determine a plant's phenotype simply by growing it and observing it! This is how Gregor Mendel, the father of genetics, studied them in 1866.

## Mutations
Plants treated with [color=cyan]unstable mutagen[/color] will undergo random genetic mutations that can change their genes and alter their traits. You can preserve plants with the mutations you want by collecting their seeds.

The more unstable mutagen you use, the more mutations you'll get. Since many genes are vital to plant survival, most mutations will result in plant death.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="UnstableMutagenChemistryBottle"/>
</Box>

## Cross-pollination
You can use a [color=cyan]sterile mouth swab[/color] to transfer pollen from one plant to another. Plants that are cross-pollinated have a chance of passing on traits. Be careful when reusing swabs; pollen is sticky!

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="BoxMouthSwab"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="DiseaseSwab"/>
</Box>

## Useful Chemicals
Several chemicals directly affect plant growth and soil quality.

<Box>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="Fertilizer"/>
</Box>
Compost is also a source of fertilizer and is obtained by decomposing animal manure. It is useful for keeping beds productive and for basic farming recipes.

## Available Plants

Below is a list of plants that can be grown in Nuclear 14. Seeds can be found while exploring the Wasteland, traded from merchants, or harvested from wild plants.

## Food and Crop Plants

Seeds can be found while exploring the Wasteland, traded from merchants, or harvested from wild plants. Click any seed entry below to see what it produces and how to grow it.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildAgaveClippingSeed" Caption="Wild Agave"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildBananaYuccaClippingSeed" Caption="Banana Yucca"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildBarrelCactusClippingSeed" Caption="Barrel Cactus"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildBlackberryClippingSeed" Caption="Blackberry"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildBrocFlowerClippingSeed" Caption="Broc Flower"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildBuffaloGourdClippingSeed" Caption="Buffalo Gourd"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildCabbageClippingSeed" Caption="Cabbage"/>
</Box>
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildCarrotClippingSeed" Caption="Carrot"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildGlowpepperClippingSeed" Caption="Glowpepper"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildMaizeClippingSeed" Caption="Maize / Corn"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildHoneyMesquiteClippingSeed" Caption="Honey Mesquite"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildMutfruitClippingSeed" Caption="Mutfruit"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildNettleClippingSeed" Caption="Nettle"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildOnionClippingSeed" Caption="Onion"/>
</Box>
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildPinyonClippingSeed" Caption="Pinyon"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildPricklyPearClippingSeed" Caption="Prickly Pear"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildRazorgrainClippingSeed" Caption="Razorgrain"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildStarlightBerryClippingSeed" Caption="Starlight Berries"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildTarberryClippingSeed" Caption="Tarberries"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildTatoClippingSeed" Caption="Tato"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildXanderRootClippingSeed" Caption="Xander Root"/>
</Box>

## Medicinal and Industrial Plants

These plants have healing, toxic, or crafting-related uses. Handle with care.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildCoyoteTobaccoClippingSeed" Caption="Coyote Tobacco"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraDaturaClippingSeed" Caption="Datura"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraWildWhiteHorsenettleClippingSeed" Caption="White Horsenettle"/>
</Box>
</Document>