<Document>
# Medicine

Medicine and chems are essential for surviving the Wasteland. Knowing what to use and when can mean the difference between life and death. Most medical supplies can be found in first aid kits, looted from enemies, or purchased from traveling doctors and merchants — but the craftable ones can mean the difference between life and death when you're far from civilization.

## Tools

A mortar and pestle is required to process ingredients for many medical recipes. Craft one from two wooden planks.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14MortarpestleGrinder" Caption="Mortar and Pestle"/>
</Box>

Ingredients:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="MaterialWoodPlank1"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="MaterialWoodPlank1"/>
</Box>

## Wound Care

[color=#a4885c]Dirty gauze[/color] is a last-resort wound dressing. It stops bleeding but carries a risk of infection. Craft it from cloth strips.

<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14DirtyGauze1" Caption="Dirty Gauze"/>

Ingredients:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="MaterialCloth1"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="MaterialCloth1"/>
</Box>

[color=#a4885c]Clean gauze[/color] is usually found in first aid kits and medical caches. [color=#a4885c]Ointment[/color] treats burns and cold damage, and can either be scavenged or brewed in the field from agave nectar, clean water, and ash.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14CleanGauze1" Caption="Clean Gauze"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14Ointment1" Caption="Ointment"/>
</Box>

Ointment reagents:
<Box>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="ExtractAgaveNectar"/>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="Water"/>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="Ash"/>
</Box>

## Healing Powder

A tribal remedy that accelerates natural healing. Nauseating but effective. Craft it from broc flower and xander root — no workbench required, just crush them together.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14HealingPowder" Caption="Healing Powder"/>
</Box>

Ingredients:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildBrocFlower"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildXander"/>
</Box>

## Cleansing Powder

A field remedy used by tribal and Legion healers to purge radiation. Craft it from one irradiated cave fungus and one xander root in the medical tab of the crafting menu.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14CleansingPowder" Caption="Cleansing Powder"/>
</Box>

Ingredients:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildCaveFungusRad"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildXander"/>
</Box>

## Healing Poultice

A more advanced natural remedy combining multiple plant extracts. Heals common ailments slowly but surpasses healing powder for sustained recovery.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14HealingPoultice" Caption="Healing Poultice"/>
</Box>

Ingredients:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildBrocFlower"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildXander"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildCaveFungus"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildAgave"/>
</Box>

## Stimpaks

[color=#a4885c]Stimpaks[/color] are the backbone of Wasteland medicine — injectable serums that rapidly accelerate the body's healing. Craft a standard stimpak by combining broc flower and xander root with a syringe and a bloodpack. If you are working from loose reagents, the herbal base is first mixed into healing mixture and then stabilized with oil and phosphorus to finish the syringe.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14Stimpak" Caption="Stimpak"/>
</Box>

Ingredients:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildBrocFlower"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildXander"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14ChemicalSyringe"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="Bloodpack"/>
</Box>

Chemistry intermediates and improvised variants:
<Box>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="HealingMixture"/>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="DirtyStimpak"/>
</Box>

[color=#a4885c]Dirty stimpaks[/color] can also be improvised with wasteland blood if you are desperate. [color=#a4885c]Super stimpaks[/color] remain pre-war or professionally manufactured goods sold by doctors and traders.

## Bitterdrink

A bottled tribal remedy for poison and radiation exposure. In practice, it is brewed from broc flower and xander root and poured into an empty soda bottle.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14Bitterdrink" Caption="Bitterdrink"/>
</Box>

Ingredients:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildBrocFlower"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FloraProduceWildXander"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14DrinkNukaColaEmpty" Caption="Empty Soda Bottle"/>
</Box>

Chemistry reference:
<Box>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="Bitterdrink"/>
</Box>

Chemistry station note: if you are working in a proper lab, you can print an empty bitterdrink bottle and fill it through the ChemMaster instead of hand-assembling it from a scavenged soda bottle.

## Jet Inhaler

A Jet inhaler is a crafting component used to make a RadAway inhaler. The crafting recipe makes the empty inhaler body from a sheet of plastic.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14JetInhaler" Caption="Jet Inhaler"/>
</Box>

Ingredients:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="SheetPlastic"/>
</Box>

<!-- #Misfits Fix: Hydra recipe corrected to match actual implementation. Previous entry incorrectly showed Jet + Turbo inhalers. Actual recipe: fill empty HydraInhaler with 15u Hydra reagent (ScorpionTail + ExtractFungus + NightstalkerBlood via chemistry), then seal with screwdriver. -->
## Hydra

Hydra requires chemistry first. Mix radscorpion tail, cave fungus extract, and nightstalker blood at a chemistry set to produce Hydra reagent (2 units per batch — you need 8 batches to reach the 15u required). Once you have 15u of Hydra, pour it into an empty hydra inhaler, then seal it with a screwdriver in the medical tab of the crafting menu.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14Hydra" Caption="Hydra"/>
</Box>

Chemistry reagents (per batch → 2u Hydra):
<Box>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="ScorpionTail"/>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="ExtractFungus"/>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="NightstalkerBlood"/>
</Box>

Assembly:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14HydraInhaler" Caption="Empty Hydra Inhaler (fill with 15u Hydra, then seal with screwdriver)"/>
</Box>

## RadAway Inhaler

Flushes radiation from the bloodstream. Assemble the inhaler body first (see Jet Inhaler above), then attach a RadAway phial loaded with RadAway reagent.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14RadAwayInhaler" Caption="RadAway Inhaler"/>
</Box>

Assembly steps:
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14JetInhaler"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14RadAwayPhial"/>
</Box>

[color=#a4885c]RadAway[/color] itself is mixed from irradiated fungus extract, antiseptic, and water. If supplies are tight, you can water it down into a weaker diluted RadAway.

<Box>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="RadAway"/>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="RadAwayDiluted"/>
</Box>

[color=#a4885c]RadAway phials[/color] and [color=#a4885c]RadAway bloodbags[/color] are also found as standalone items throughout the Wasteland.

## Antidotes and Other Remedies

Most finished items in this section are found or purchased — looted from enemies, bought from traveling doctors, or discovered in medical caches across the Wasteland. The chemistry itself can still be refined if you have the right ingredients.

[color=#a4885c]Antidote chemistry[/color] starts with radscorpion tail and ethanol to make antidote mixture, then uses tarberries to refine it into proper antidote.

<Box>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="AntidoteMixture"/>
<GuideReagentEmbed Reagent="Antidote"/>
</Box>

Chemistry station note: empty antidote bottles can also be printed at a chemistry station and filled directly once you have a finished antidote batch.

Not every item in this section is a straightforward treatment. Mourning poultice is included here because it is a field compound you may find alongside medical supplies, but its purpose is ritual rather than restorative. It is primarily associated with Legion and tribal ceremonial use: a poisonous herbal mixture meant to induce visions and altered speech, carrying clear negative connotations and causing minor physical harm instead of healing.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14Antidote" Caption="Antidote"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14SmellingSalts" Caption="Smelling Salts"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14MourningPoultice" Caption="Mourning Poultice"/>
</Box>

## Pills, Canisters, and Chems

Pills and canisters are pre-manufactured and cannot be crafted. They are found in medical caches, purchased from doctors, or looted from enemies.

<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14RadXCanisterFilled" Caption="Rad-X"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14BuffoutCanisterFilled" Caption="Buffout"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14MentatsCanisterFilled" Caption="Mentats"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14FixerCanisterFilled" Caption="Fixer"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14CateyeCanisterFilled" Caption="Cateye"/>
</Box>
<Box>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14Jet" Caption="Jet"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14Hydra" Caption="Hydra"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14BuffjetCanisterFilled" Caption="Buffjet"/>
<GuideEntityEmbed Entity="N14BufftatsCanisterFilled" Caption="Bufftats"/>
</Box>

[color=#a4885c]Warning:[/color] Prolonged chem use leads to addiction. Fixer can treat most addictions, but availability is not guaranteed.
</Document>
