<Document>
# Vault Dwellers

Vault-Tec Corporation constructed over a hundred underground vaults before the Great War of 2077 — ostensibly to shelter the American population, but in reality to conduct controlled sociological and scientific experiments on sealed communities over generations. Most vaults were designed to introduce a hidden variable: extreme isolation, internal predators, psychological manipulation, or resource scarcity. The results were meant to be observed.

The vault in this region has survived intact. Its residents have lived in regulated isolation, largely unaware of how the surface world has changed — or of what their vault was ultimately designed to do to them.

## Life in the Vault

All vault functions flow through the Overseer's authority. Vault systems are aging but functional. A critical component failure could force the door open — beginning a contact with the surface world that changes everything.

## Roles

<ColorBox Color="#0d47a1">
  <Box Margin="2">
  [bold]Overseer[/bold]
  </Box>
</ColorBox>
<Box>
[color=#a4885c]Your role:[/color] Administer the vault. You know something the others may not — the vault's true purpose, if one exists. Decide whether to shield your people from that knowledge or lead them through it. If the door opens, you determine how your community meets the surface world.
</Box>

<ColorBox Color="#0d47a1">
  <Box Margin="2">
  [bold]Vault Security[/bold]
  </Box>
</ColorBox>
<Box>
[color=#a4885c]Your role:[/color] Maintain order inside the vault and protect it if the door opens. You enforce the Overseer's authority. How you use that authority — with justice or with fear — shapes what the vault becomes.
</Box>

<ColorBox Color="#0d47a1">
  <Box Margin="2">
  [bold]Vault Scientist[/bold]
  </Box>
</ColorBox>
<Box>
[color=#a4885c]Your role:[/color] Keep vault systems running, conduct research, and provide medical care. You may hold critical information about the vault's experiment — and that knowledge could save or destroy your community depending on what you choose to do with it.
</Box>

<ColorBox Color="#0d47a1">
  <Box Margin="2">
  [bold]Vault Dweller[/bold]
  </Box>
</ColorBox>
<Box>
[color=#a4885c]Your role:[/color] Live vault life. Follow protocols, contribute to community work, and try to make sense of what is happening. If the door opens, every assumption you have about the world will be tested — starting immediately.
</Box>

## Relations

Vault Dwellers begin the round in isolation. If the door opens, how they engage the surface world depends on the Overseer's judgment and the vault's experiment parameters. Other factions will be curious, calculating, or hostile — depending on what they believe the vault contains.
</Document>
